Introduction

P ersonality style is the essence of who you are and how
you approach life. Knowing your personality style pro-
vides useful insight into how you communicate, lead others,
work in teams, and a host of other interactions. Your person-
ality style is the foundation for what’s commonly referred to
as “people skills.”

Personality styles are based on the blending of your assertive
and expressive behavior. These behaviors occur in patterns
over time and across situations. Use these insights to increase
your personal effectiveness and enrich working with others.

About This Book

Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition, provides
an overview of the four personality styles and then examines
how these styles affect how you behave in a variety of work-
place situations. Use this book as a guide to learn about the
four personality styles and how these styles work in coaching,
leading, communicating, selling, teaming, time management,
and learning.

HRDQ has devoted considerable research and resources to
this topic, and it is this body of work that provides the foun-
dation for the chapters in this book. Throughout, I reference
the HRDQ Style Model to introduce and illustrate the charac-
teristics, benefits, and potential trouble spots associated with
each style.

About HRDO

Better Learning. Better Performance. Better Life. That’s why
HRDQ does what it does. HRDQ’s vision isn’t something that
its marketing people pulled out of a hat. The vision has a spe-
cific meaning.

2 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

A trusted developer for more than 30 years, HRDQ specializes
in experiential learning resources that help you develop the
people skills you need to become a better communicator, a
better leader, a better negotiator, and a better team member.
Experiential learning is better learning because it raises the
odds that what you learn will transfer to your job — where

it counts. HRDQ assessments, games, simulations, and pro-
grams put you in situations that allow you to discover new
skills — and then practice them.

The result? Practice in the learning environment leads to
application in the workplace because it gives you the ability
and the self-confidence to use and refine the skill in the real
world. You've been there. You've done it. You know you can
do it again. And that leads to better performance. From better
performance comes growth and success, which leads to a
better life.

We aren’t referring only to higher salaries, promotions, and
status. We mean simply this: Any activity, any task, or any job
is far more rewarding when you can perform it skillfully. And
isn’t life more fun when you can do things well?

Check out HRDQ at HRDQstore. com or call (800) 633-4533 for
more information.

How This Book Is Organized

The 12 chapters of this book move from an introduction of
the four personality styles to the application of those styles
in various work situations. You even get a few chapters at the
end with some tips and tricks of personality style.

You're encouraged to read the first two chapters in order, but
like any For Dummies book, you don’t have to. Try visiting the
remaining chapters as the topic becomes important to you.
You can jump in wherever best suits your knowledge needs —
check out the Table of Contents at the beginning of this book
to see where you want to go. Or, as with most books, you can
start at the beginning and read all the way to the end, if you
want.

Introduction 3

Icons Used in This Book

The following icons are used in this book:

The information in paragraphs marked by the Remember icon
is important and may be repeated for emphasis. This way, you
can easily spot the information when you refer to the book
later.

MBER
SS
&

Tips identify timesaving suggestions or better ways to do
things. These tidbits can also help you interact with others or
better understand yourself. So keep an eye out for this icon.

The Warning icon includes information that may keep you
from making some mistakes with other personality types. The
information here can also help you out in some precarious
situations.

The Technical Stuff icon represents information that’s pro-
vided for additional review. You don’t have to read it, but for
the techie folks out there, the info here is like getting a bonus!
Use this information for deeper exploration, if you wish.

Where to Go from Here

As you clarify your own style, jump to the chapter that’s

of most interest to you right now. It may be coaching, lead-
ing, communicating, teaming, selling, time management, or
learning. Each is covered in its own chapter. Also, check out
Chapters 10, 11, and 12 for some quick tips and top lists for
more interactions with the different personality types.

/} Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 1
Defining Personality Style

In This Chapter

» Getting a primer on the basics of personality style

» Understanding the behaviors that combine to make up your style

» Assessing the four personality styles

RE EE HE wa Bis WEEE WE He ar Es i WWE HE HE

f you observe people, you may notice that certain pre-

dictable patterns and tendencies exist in their behaviors.
These patterns enable you to have some degree of certainty
in how people may behave as you interact with them. And as
you may know, if it’s true of “them,” it’s true of you.

These patterns of behavior in people are called personality. In
this chapter, you discover the roots of personality type, the
role of expressiveness and assertiveness in formulating your
personality style, and the basics of the four personality style
patterns.

Familiarizing Yourself with the
Basics of Personality Style

Personality has been a subject of interest from the very begin-
nings of civilization. The earliest notions of personality sug-
gested that individuals were born with ways of being in the
world (Navajo). The Greek physician Hippocrates (460-370
BC) codified these “ways of being” into a medical theory
based on temperaments — certain innate human moods,
emotions, and behaviors. Modern psychology has provided
numerous other empirically framed theories of personality.

6 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Carl Gustav Jung and William Moulton Marston are among the
most widely known of the psychologists who’ve increased the
understanding of personality. Jung’s ideas formed the basis of
the Myers-Briggs Type Indicator assessment, while Marston
was responsible for developing the DISC model.

Current theories are grouped into the following categories:

vr Psychodynamic

vr‘ Behavioral

vw Situation or social driven patterns

vv Existential (or patterns to make meaning of life)

As you may imagine, plenty of researchers and writers have
talked about these points of view, which are rich and complex
theories. Many of the theories address two core qualities of
personality:

vr Sources within the person that drive efforts to control or
be part of his environment (degrees of assertiveness)

vr How much social connection or engagement individuals
typically display (degrees of expressiveness)

Depending on your take of the qualities and how they blend, a
host of models exist to give greater refinements to these twin
dimensions of personality.

Observers and researchers of personality also have explored
the roles of family history, genetic traits, and learning in the
development of typical personality patterns and not so typical
patterns — or what’s categorized as dysfunctional personalities.
For example, everyone is motivated by self-interest, but the nar-
cissist goes too far in self-promotion and self-indulgence.

Do a web search on personality and personality styles. You
can access thorough information on all the theories of per-
sonality and how they were developed. A deeper look into the
roots of personality gives you an appreciation for the different
ways of seeing personality patterns.

The current theories are accessible and interesting but not
as helpful in the day-to-day interactions as simply asking,
“Whatever the underlying source, what can I see that helps

Chapter 1: Defining Personality Style 7

me understand my interactions with others consistently over
time?” Personality style is a way of approaching personality
patterns without delving into other psychological issues.

By paying attention to style, you can efficiently and effectively
achieve three things:

1. Quickly identify patterns in yourself and others.

2. Link style to important life experiences, such as learn-
ing, coaching, and leading.

3. Flex the aspects of behavior that are more effective in
dealing with others.

Knowing What Makes Up a Style

You have a preferred personality style that developed over time.
Your style reflects how you like to work — alone or with others —
how you spend your time — talking or reading — and how you
deal with and share information. Your style is essentially the way
you act when you're able to do things your own way.

Your preferred style is likely to be used most of the time —
that’s why it’s “preferred”; however, you may decide to
behave differently from your style from time to time. You're
likely to be more effective when you capitalize on the benefits
of your style and also flex or adapt your style to account for
the style of the person with whom you wish to interact.

Your style is determined by the degree of assertiveness and
expressiveness you demonstrate. Assertiveness is essentially
the effort that you make to influence or control the thoughts
and actions of others. Expressiveness is the effort you make to
control emotions and feelings when relating to others.

Check out Tables 1-1 and 1-2. They're a quick and easy way
to determine your own preference for using these behaviors.
Circle where you feel you fall on the Expressive and Assertive
continua. The ratings are as follows:

vr 1: You rarely show this behavior.

vr 5: You show the behavior sometimes.

vr 9: You show the behavior all the time in almost every
situation. ;

8 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Table 1-1 The Expressive Continuum
Low Expressiveness High Expressiveness
(Controls Emotions) (Displays Emotions)

1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9

Table 1-2 The Assertive Continuum

Low Assertiveness High Assertiveness
(Asks for Information) (Tells What’s Important)

1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9

If you’ve taken a look at the tables, then you can plot your
self-estimated scores on the vertical and horizontal axes in
Figure 1-1. Mark with an X where the two scores intersect. You
should end up with an X in one of the four quadrants.

Assertiveness
(high)
9
8
7
Es 35
25 1 | 2 | 3 | 4|5|6 78|9|32
oO — =
2 A S
Ld Ll
3
2
1
Assertiveness
(low)

Figure 1-1: The diagram model of assertiveness versus expressiveness.

Chapter 1: Defining Personality Style 9

Checking Out the Four
Personality Styles

Your style affects how you sell, coach, influence, manage time,
lead, and learn; it even helps you engage in relationships and
identify a career choice. While your style doesn’t predict your
behavior or your choices, it gives you a handle on behavior in
pragmatic ways and provides you with a foundation of under-
standing for how you tend to operate.

Getting acquainted with your own style has the added benetfit
of helping you identify the styles of those around you. By
understanding the elements of personality style, you have a
greater chance at building and maintaining the relationships
and connections that matter in your life. In this section, I
cover the different personality types, so maybe you can start
to see which type you are. For a deeper discussion of the per-
sonality types, see Chapter 2.

If you read the preceding section and completed your ratings,
you can see that four relative patterns emerge, illustrated in
Figure 1-2.

On the HRDQ style model, your behaviors fall into four differ-
ent quadrants:

vr Top left-hand quadrant: High assertive and low expres-
sive behaviors fall into this quadrant. If you happen to
land here, you may show your style by telling others
information, and you're able to control emotions. This
pattern usually results in an individual having a Direct
Style.

» Top right-hand quadrant: This quadrant contains the
high assertive and high expressive behaviors, which are
typically demonstrated by telling others information and
displaying your emotions. This pattern results in an indi-
vidual having a Spirited Style.

vr Bottom left-hand quadrant: If you fall in this quadrant,
you show low assertive and low expressive behaviors.
You demonstrate these qualities by asking others for
information and controlling emotions. This pattern usu-
ally results in an individual having a Systematic Style.

7 0 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Style.

Direct

Systematic

Figure 1-2: The HRDQ Style Model.

i

Considerate

vv Bottom right-hand quadrant: This quadrant contains the
low assertive and high expressive behaviors. People in
this area tend to ask others for information and display
their emotions. This pattern is called the Considerate

The four patterns suggest four kinds of questions you could
ask yourself to make sure you use the wisdom of the styles.
Think of the styles as lenses of experience when working with
others. Check out Table 1-3 for more information.

Table 1-3 The Four Lenses of Experience

Lens Insight Question

Direct Taking action Am | moving toward a spe-
cific goal?

Spirited Engagement with Have | included and inspired

others everyone needed for this

activity?

Systematic Being thorough Have | covered all of the

bases?

Considerate

Showing compassion

Have | shown interest in and
care for others?

Chapter 1: Defining Personality Style 7 7

Keep in mind that your style is automatic and natural to the
way you get things done. While your style is typical of you, it
isn’t always evident, because you’ve learned to flex from time
to time. No doubt you can recall a time when you were more
or less assertive than typical or more or less expressive than
usual, but you flex your style in order to respond to a situ-
ation where you realize your preferred style may not be as
effective.

Smile: You're on camera

If there were small video clips of you your personality style. The more you
‘throughout the day, in many different understand about your style, the
situations, you'd be pretty consistent greater your chance of knowing
in how often you ask or tell and show when and how to capitalize on your
or hold back your emotional reac- styles benefits.
tions. This consistent pattern reflects

7 2 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 2
Deciphering Your

» Understanding the elements of the different styles
» Getting a handle on the benefits and trouble spots within each style

(Gene acquainted with your own style helps you in
many areas of your life. Knowing your style affects

how you sell, coach, influence, manage time, lead, and learn.
It can even help you in your relationships and your career
path. While your style doesn’t predict your behavior or your
choices, it provides a foundation of understanding for how
you function.

In this chapter, you discover the ins and outs of each style:
Direct, Spirited, Systematic, and Considerate. You also see
how you're flexible within your own style. There may be a few
trouble spots, as well, but don’t worry; I point those out too.

Looking at the Elements
of the Direct Style

If you have the tendency to say that you know what needs
to be done, when it needs to be done, and how it should be
done, then you're using a Direct Style. This style demon-
strates a very straightforward and decisive approach during

14 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

interactions. Generally, individuals with this style seem tough
minded, are focused on what needs to get done, and prefer to
complete tasks quickly.

The Direct Style is based on being assertive and controlled
in expressing your emotions. Direct Style is high on assertive
and low on expressive behaviors. For more on where this
style lands on the style continuum, see Chapter 1.

Direct Style has the following characteristics:

vr Take charge

vw Get results — now!

vr Compete with vigor

vw Organize tasks for practical outcomes
vr Pursue risks confidently

Individuals of the Direct Style walk fast, speak fast, and assert
control.

Noticing the trouble spots
of the Direct Style

All styles bring benefits and potential trouble spots. The trou-
ble spots can begin to outweigh the perceived value of the
style unless the individual learns how to moderate the style
and flex.

Flexing your style means adjusting your instinctual behavior
to achieve the desired result. If you don’t flex, you're likely
to experience frustration and disappointment in many situa-
tions, as will those around you. See the section “Making the
Direct Style flex” for more information.

The Direct Style isn’t without trouble spots. Often those who
prefer the Direct Style are unaware that their behaviors trig-
ger reactions that can create problems. Some of the trouble
spots include the following:

vr Being perceived as a poor listener

vr Appearing impatient and terse with others

Chapter 2: Deciphering Your Personality Style 7 5

= WM” Arguing without being open to new information or ideas
vr Competing at all costs

vr Discounting others’ feelings, reactions, and perceptions

vr Showing disinterest in collaboration

Making the Direct Style flex

Flexing the Direct Style has two avenues: reducing the degree
of assertiveness and increasing emotional expressions of
warmth and regard. The Direct Style is useful in situations
when you need to:

wv Get to the bottom line quickly

vr Speak forcefully (as in preventing an accident)

. V Assert control to communicate authority and direction

Those with the Direct Style need to calibrate how much asser-
tive behavior is appropriate and how much emotional energy
to show in certain situations. For example, demonstrating a
Direct Style while dealing with an immediate crisis works very
well, but it may not be as effective when dealing with change
when people’s emotional needs may need to be considered.

Understanding the Elements
of the Spirited Style

BE
N R

The Spirited Style is based on being assertive and emotionally
expressive. For more on where this style lands on the style
continuum, see Chapter 1.

The Spirited Style has the following characteristics:

vw Inspires ideas and possibilities by sharing illustrative
stories, working fast, and providing a fresh perspective

vw Builds alliances quickly with others

vr Persuades others by using enthusiasm and personal
touches

16 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

=” Motivates and engages others by focusing on the big pic-
ture and lively, energetic presentations

Identifying the trouble spots

The Spirited Style has some challenging areas, as well. Some
of the trouble spots individuals who fall in this category need
to manage are

vr Being perceived as overly dramatic

vr Generalizing and ignoring important details

vr Missing deadlines

vr Exaggerating and missing important information

vr Being overly enthusiastic, leading to miscommunication
about important points

Flexing the Spirited Style

Flexing the Spirited Style requires you to rein in your asser-
tive or expressive behaviors in some situations. Because

the Spirited Style uses high degrees of both assertive and
expressive behaviors, it’s important to read the situations and
people you're dealing with to see if you may need to tone it
down a little. The Spirited Style is useful in situations where
you need to

vr Generate enthusiasm about ideas and possibilities

vr Inspire commitment to key goals and visions

vw Strengthen alliances to keep everyone working in the
same direction

vr Rally support for pursuing key objectives

Those with the Spirited Style should adjust how much asser-
tive behavior is appropriate and how much emotional energy
to exhibit, depending on their surroundings. For example,
demonstrating a Spirited Style while making a presentation
to introduce an exciting new product works very well, but
this style may not work so well when the negative results of a
health and safety audit need to be explained.

Chapter 2: Deciphering Your Personality Style 7 7

Sifting through the
Systematic Style

Careful planning and thorough organization in your approach
to getting things done are the key elements of the Systematic
Style. This style pays close attention to details, efficiency,
and careful problem-solving. Generally, individuals with this
style seem very focused on priorities and make sure to follow
guidelines or standard operating procedures.

The Systematic Style is based on being more focused on inter-
nal awareness than externally asserting ideas or information
and controlling emotions. The Systematic Style is the result of
low assertive and low emotionally expressive behaviors. For
more on where this style lands on the style continuum, see
Chapter 1.

The Systematic Style has the following characteristics:

Wr Follows the guidelines and standard procedures
vr Gets results by working efficiently
vr Organizes details, steps, and processes

vr Makes decisions using verified facts and reliable methods

vr Pursues high standards through careful analysis

Spotting the trouble areas

The Systematic Style brings about certain challenges. Often
those who prefer the Systematic Style are unaware that their
behavior triggers reactions that can create problems.

Some of the trouble spots include the following:

vr Being perceived as impersonal and cold
vr Appearing disinterested in interacting with others

vr Seeming overly reliant on tried-and-true procedures at
the cost of new ideas and innovation

vw Failing to build collaborative relationships

78 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Knowing how to flex the
Systematic Style

If you fall into the Systematic Style category, make sure to
pay attention to when you need to elevate assertive behavior
and how much emotional energy to show when working with
others. The Systematic Style is useful in situations when you
need to

vr Make sure a thorough, analytical approach is provided

vw Rely on controlled, methodical decision-making

vr Use a well-organized and efficient problem-solving

. approach

Flexing the Systematic Style has two avenues: increasing the
degree of being assertive and increasing emotional expres-
sions of warmth and regard. For example, demonstrating a
Systematic Style while implementing a business plan works
very well, but it may not work so well when dealing with activ-
ities to boost team enthusiasm and commitment.

Comprehending the
Considerate Style

Do you have the desire to know what everyone else is think-
ing, and do you seek to build relationships by being friendly
and accommodating? If so, you've landed yourself in the
Considerate Style. This style demonstrates a high emotional
expressiveness and very little assertiveness. If you display
this style, you typically are thoughtful, trusting, caring, and
supportive of others.

The benefits of the Considerate Style are numerous.
Individuals who prefer this style often demonstrate a keen
interest in working with others and building relationships.
Individuals with this style like to work with others to get
things done.

The Considerate Style has the following characteristics:

Chapter 2: Deciphering Your Personality Style 7 9

vw Listens to others

vr Gets results through teams
vr Collaborates and values relationships
vr Supports others

vw Prefers a gentle, “steady as you go” approach

Uncovering the trouble spots
of the Considerate Style

People who fall into the Considerate Style may have a few
issues. Some of these include the following:

WING!
&

vr Being perceived as conflict-avoidant

vr“ Appearing to give in rather than “put a stake in the
ground” on issues

vr Overemphasizing feelings at the cost of analyzing issues
vr Unwilling to express opinions for fear of offending others
vr Telling others what they want to hear

vr Showing little interest in facts, analysis, and debate

Managing your style

Those with the Considerate Style need to consider the
amount of assertive behavior that is appropriate and how
much emotional energy to show in a presenting situation. For
example, demonstrating a Considerate Style while seeking to
initiate open sharing or discussions with a team is likely to be
very effective.

The Considerate Style is useful in situations when you need to

=” Strengthen team relationships

vr Address the personal needs of others

. V Coach others with supportive and caring language

Flexing the Considerate Style includes increasing your
degree of assertiveness and decreasing your emotional
expressiveness.

2 0 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 3

Applying the Four Styles
In Communication

( ommunicating means that you're trying to get your
ideas, perceptions, or explanations understood the way

you intended. You're likely to feel that communication was
“clear” when the meaning of what was said is mutually under-
stood. You achieve this understanding through several dimen-
sions of communicating.

Interestingly, communication involves more than the words
you use. Some experts argue that up to 70 percent of the
meaning people take from your efforts to communicate come
from your paraverbal (voice tone) and nonverbal behaviors
(facial expressions and body language). Your paraverbal
behavior — the way you say what you want to share — is cen-
tral to getting your message across. Your body language —
nonverbal behavior — covers everything from how you shake
hands to facial expressions and is part of your communication
style.

Your communication style is the product of the mixture of your
assertiveness and emotional expressiveness that makes your
personality style, which is blended with all of the other aspects
of communication. In other words, each style has general
patterns in paraverbals and nonverbals, which are important
to understand.

22 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

After you've decided the message you want to give to an indi-
vidual or to a group, you need to attend to the basic elements
of communicating a message:

vw Establishing a connection with the audience of one or
one thousand, making sure that the reason for the com-
munication is clear

vw Creating a common understanding of the message being
delivered and received

vw Facilitating the exploration of the implications of the
communication

vr Wrapping up the message and verifying common
understanding

As you engage in each of these elements of communicating,
the use of your personality style reveals your communica-
tion style. Importantly, learning to flex your personality style
enhances your communication effectiveness as you engage
with others through each element of communication.

All communication styles can be equally effective. Also, com-
munication styles that don’t match the needs of the audience
or receiver of the communication can result in a failed com-
munication. You need to understand the benefits and poten-
tial challenges each style tends to demonstrate, inclusive of
paraverbal and nonverbal behavior.

Communication is complex. You have to consider the mes-
sage that your words, tone, and body language give to your
audience. All of it is magnified by your personality style.

The Ins and Outs of the
Four Personality Styles
in Communication

Communication tactics are a direct result of your personality
style. In this section, you review the four personality styles in
communication and see how each style provides a useful way
to get your message across. You also discover the potential

Chapter 3: Applying the Four Styles in Communication 23

challenges you may encounter with your style if you don’t
learn to flex it in communication.

Direct Style

The Direct Style works best when the audience or recipient
of the message needs direction and responds well to asser-
tive and low expressive behaviors. Individuals with this style
tend to speak quickly and loudly, give direct eye contact, and
display forms of power through their attire and by keeping
physical distance.

A few benefits of this style in communication include

confident direction
vr Assertively outlining a plan of action in the message

= V Energetically focusing on the end result and why you
need to do as directed

You may also notice a few trouble spots:

_ v» Appears impatient, which interferes with establishing
rapport

vr Seems overly critical, which interferes with mutual
understanding

vw Displays aggressive behavior, which interferes with the
audience’s feeling heard or supported

This style doesn’t work well when the audience or recipient of
the message is looking for an expressive, warm, and facilita-
tive communicator.

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style works best when the audience or recipient
of the message enjoys spontaneity, enthusiastic brainstorm-
ing, and emotional expressiveness. Individuals with this style
tend to be animated, have a lot of voice inflection and display
movement during interactions, and express views readily.

24 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Take notice of these benefits:

» Creative thinking with many ideas and turns of phrase

vr Spontaneously expressive, and uses warm, supportive
language, which generates enthusiasm

ws Identifies how messages fit into a larger message or
context

But take caution with the trouble areas:

= v» Energy and enthusiasm may overwhelm others, prevent-
ing them from sharing their perspectives

vr Tends to avoid planning, details, and drilling down into
the particulars of a situation

ww Seen as impulsive and disorganized, prompting the audi-
ence to feel that the message isn’t clear

This type of person doesn’t work well when the audience

or recipient of the message wants organized and pragmatic
information. Audiences or recipients of messages who need a
planned approach to understanding the communication don’t
work well with this style.

Systematic Style

When the audience or recipient of the message wants a
detailed and thoroughly factual message is when this style
hits a home run. Audiences who respond best with this style
want an objective, methodical communication strategy.
Individuals with this style tend to provide precise statements,
brief comments with little emotional expression, little anima-
tion, and keep physical distance.

Folks who favor this style display the following benefits in
communication:

vr Thorough attention to process and details in giving the
message and in the message itself

vr Factual and pragmatic, concise and precise messages

. v Careful, patient, reserved in delivering information

Chapter 3: Applying the Four Styles in Communication 2 5

Whoa! Watch out, though. Every style has some issues that
may conflict with other styles. Check these out:

vr Reluctance to try new approaches, relying on tried-and-
true ways, which may lose the attention of the listener

vr Takes too much time to work through each element of a
communication and often undercommunicates informa-
tion, producing confusion and doubt

vr May fail to see the long-term big picture and fail to share
important personal information

This style doesn’t work well when the audience or recipient of
the message needs more warmth and initiating behavior from
the communicator. Audiences or recipients of messages who
are looking for mutual brainstorming and exploration of ideas
may find this style difficult during interactions.

Considerate Style

People who display the Considerate Style interact best when
audiences or recipients of messages want an empathetic, sup-
portive, and encouraging interaction. Audiences who need a
friendly relationship work well with this style. Individuals with
this style tend to talk slowly, use soft tones, and like close
personal contact.

When communicating, the person of the Considerate Style
shows these pluses:
vr Pursues collaborative relationships to build trust

vw Listens actively and provides support during all stages of
the communication

vr Encourages team members and demonstrates caring for
others’ needs

Do take time to heed the trouble areas of this communication
style, though:

vr Overly focused on rapport and emotional expressive-
ness, which leads to less time for sharing concrete
information

2 6 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

=” Lack of directness may result in a lack of clarity during
communication

vr Rather than communicating directly and with initiative,
may spend too much time trying to facilitate personal
connections

The Considerate Communication Style doesn’t work well with
audiences or recipients of messages who want a less personal,
“all business” approach. This style tends to remain agreeable
and avoid conflict. Audiences or recipients of messages who
are looking for new insight or opinions find this style difficult
during interactions.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Communication

To increase overall effectiveness, you need to learn to flex
your communication style as the situation requires. For exam-
ple, the following elements of communicating may be more
efficiently achieved with different styles:

vw Establishing a connection with the audience and making
sure that the reason for the communication is clear is
effectively achieved with the Considerate Style

ws Creating a common understanding of the message being
delivered and received is effectively achieved with the
Systematic Style

vw Facilitating the exploration of the implications of the
communication is effectively achieved with the Spirited
Style

vr‘ Wrapping up the message and verifying common under-
standing is effectively achieved with the Direct Style

Of course, an important determinant of effective communi-
cating is the fit of styles with the needs of the audience or
recipient of the message. If an individual with a Considerate
Style attempts to work with an individual with a Direct Style
and neither knows how to flex, the Considerate may end up
with hurt feelings while the Direct may end up frustrated.

Chapter 3: Applying the Four Styles in Communication 2 7

Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the interaction
and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a response.
You need to determine how much assertiveness and emo-
tional expressiveness is required of you in an interaction.

In addition, you will need to modify your paraverbal and
nonverbal behaviors associated with the four communication
styles.

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four communi-
cation styles are as follows:

= vw” Direct Style communication can fail to recognize that

the individual being communicated with has hurt feel-
ings due to a direct comment. Knowing when to increase
some emotional expressiveness and tone down assertive-
ness benefits those with this communication style. Also,
making sure to speak less loudly, move less quickly, and
move closer to others promotes the effectiveness of this
style.

vw Spirited Style communication can fail to recognize when
the audience wants a concrete plan and wants to know
the details about a message. Knowing when to moderate
both assertiveness (around ideas) and emotional expres-
siveness helps those with this coaching style. Also, make
sure to moderate the animated loud voice, tone down the
inflection, and show greater calm when communicating
with those whose styles are obviously different.

vr Systematic Style communication can fail to recognize
that an audience or recipient of a message wants more
brainstorming of possibilities and greater enthusiasm
about the message. Knowing when to elevate both asser-
tiveness and emotional expressiveness benefits those
with this communication style. Also, make sure to share
emotional reactions to information, engage with more
animation, and move closer to the audience.

vr Considerate Style communication can fail to recognize
that an audience or recipient of the message wants more
directness and more attention to a thoroughly planned
message than a warm, empathetic interaction. Knowing
when to elevate an assertive response and decrease emo-
tional expressiveness will benefit those with this com-
munication style. Also, make sure to enhance your voice
volume, move more quickly when physically shifting, and
be mindful of others’ personal space.

2 8 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include:

v Ask your audience if more or less assertiveness would
benefit the communication with a question such as
“Would you like for me to address all aspects of this situ-
ation now?”

1” Ask your audience if more or less emotional expressive-
ness would benefit the communication with a question
such as “How can I support your thinking through this
message?”

1” Monitor the time you spend “telling” versus “asking”
when communicating. The best communication is a “give
and take” in sharing common understanding.

vr Evaluate the pace of moving through communication
. elements and processes.

Of course the most effective communication comes from the
alignment of styles and needs between the individual send-
ing the message and the individual receiving the message.
To share information and to listen in ways that increase the
chances of understanding, you need to know your style ben-
efits and ways to flex.

Chapter 4

Applyıng the Four

= Examining the benefits and challenges of style in leading

[ cer engender commitment from others to achieve a
desired goal. Leaders influence the behavior of others to
do those things necessary to implement a plan designed to
realize a vision and achieve specific outcomes.

Being a leader has nothing to do with titles or positions in
organizations. There are people with important titles in orga-
nizations who don’t lead — they use power as an exclusive
form of influence. You can lead others at work, in the com-
munity, or at home by using the benefits of your personality
style and flexing your style to accommodate the changing
needs of those you are leading.

Leadership is complex regardless of how ambitious the vision.
Libraries of books exist focusing exclusively on the nature of
leadership. In all of the research, however, some basic ele-
ments in leading others do exist. Using these basic elements
can aid your leadership initiatives. Fundamentally, leaders
need to

v Establish a trusting relationship with individuals they
want to lead. With a relationship of trust established,
they can use their style to facilitate an understanding of
what followers need to do to reach a goal.

30 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

vr Create a common understanding of the vision and plan to
implement that specifies roles, tasks, and deliverables

vr‘ Encourage and support everyone's efforts to implement
the plan

vr Evaluate and keep everyone informed of progress toward
© the goals

As you engage in each of these elements of leading, the use of
your personality style reveals your leading style. Importantly,
learning to flex your personality style enhances your leader
effectiveness as you engage with others through each element
of leading. Your leader behavior and your personality style
make up your leader style.

All leading styles can be equally effective. Although, leading
styles that don’t match the needs of the followers can result
in a failed leadership initiative. You need to understand

the benefits and potential challenges each style tends to
demonstrate.

Checking Out the Benefits and
Trouble Spots of Each Style

Leading others means behaving in ways that inspire and
motivate people. Each of the four personality styles brings
specific benefits to leaders. When your style “fits” the leader-
ship demands of the situation and the people you're leading,
the benefits are numerous. Also, by knowing the trouble spots
of the style as they pertain to leading, you can become more
aware of what behaviors to avoid when leading others in any
situation. In this section, you find out how best to use your
style to lead others.

Direct Style

The person with this style works best when followers need
decisive direction and responds well to a fast-moving, aggres-
sive leadership approach.

Some of the benefits include the following:

Chapter 4: Applying the Four Styles in Leading 3 7

vr Produces quick results

vr Takes bold action, no matter how challenging a situation
may be

vr Energetically motivates people

The trouble spots to watch out for include

vr‘ Competitive nature interferes with establishing leader-
follower relationships

vr Seems overbearing, which interferes with mutual planning

vr Displays insensitive behaviors, which interfere with fol-
lowers feeling supported

This style doesn’t work well when followers are looking for
expressive, warm, and facilitative leaders.

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style succeeds when followers enjoy enthusiastic
motivation and a less structured approach. Other pluses of
this style in leading include the following:

w This leader motivates others to be creative and generate
fresh ideas.

w This leader is spontaneously expressive, warm, and
supportive.

vw This leader sees the big picture, context, and overall
vision.

This leader may get into trouble in the following areas:
vr Energy and enthusiasm may overwhelm others, prevent-
ing them from sharing their perspectives

vw Over eagerness can lead to glossing over of important
details

vr Seen as impulsive and disorganized prompting followers
to feel unproductive

The Spirited Style leader doesn’t work well when followers
need a planned approach to tasks, roles, and goals.

32 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Systematic Style

Systematic Style leaders perform best when followers expect
the leader to develop a detailed plan and pay attention to
data. Followers who work best with this style want an objec-
tive, methodical implementation strategy.

These leaders

vr Provide structure, objectivity, and accuracy

vr Are factual and pragmatic; followers feel information is
reliable and credible

vr Tend to be careful, patient, and reserved

Trouble spots include

1” Reluctance to try new approaches, which discourages
others from sharing new ideas

vr Taking too much time to work through each process,
which can result in losing the focus of followers

Wr Appearing impersonal or lacking in creativity due to their
L factual, detail-oriented approach

The leaders in this category don’t work well when followers
need quick decision-making or flexibility.

Considerate Style

Considerate followers want an empathetic, supportive, and
encouraging coach. Followers who need a friendly relation-
ship will work well with this style. Considerate Style leaders
work best when leaders tend to

vr‘ Provide others with a sense of reassurance in difficult or
changing times

vw Listen actively and provide support, developing a loyal
following

vr Encourage personal insight and show how each individ-
ual benefits from achieving the vision

But beware of the tendencies that leaders in this category
struggle with:

Chapter 4: Applying the Four Styles in Leading 33

vr Too much focus on rapport and emotional expressive-
ness can cause them to become overly permissive, allow-
ing difficult situations to get out of control.

vr A desire to keep things comfortable can cause them to
resist change.

vr Rather than approaching some issues directly and with
initiative, they may spend too much time trying to facili-
. tate personal insight.

These folks don’t work well when followers want a more
take-charge approach. This style tends to be overly con-
cerned with personal feelings, which doesn’t work for some
followers.

Leadership is now the most researched and written about
topic in management literature.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Leading

To increase overall effectiveness, leaders need to learn to flex
their style as the situation requires. For example, the follow-
ing elements of leading may be more efficiently achieved with
different styles:

vw Establishing a relationship is efficiently achieved with the
Considerate Style.

vw Creating a common understanding of the issue and the
strategy for addressing the desired goals easily flows
from the Systematic Style.

vr Supporting the implementation of the plan comes
naturally to the Spirited Style.

vr Monitoring progress and re-evaluating future courses of
action are effectively managed with the Direct Style.

Of course, the most important determinant of leader success
is the fit of leader style and knowledge with the needs of the
followers. If a Considerate Style leader attempts to work with
a Direct Style follower and neither knows how to flex, then the
leader-follower relationship is likely to be short lived.

30 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the interaction
and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a response.
You need to determine how much assertiveness and emo-
tional expressiveness is required of you in an interaction.

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four leading
styles are as follows:

vw Direct Style leaders can fail to recognize that a follower’s
feelings have been hurt by a direct comment or that a fol-
lower wants to move at a different pace. Knowing when
to increase emotional expressiveness and tone down
assertiveness benefits those with this leading style.

w Spirited Style leaders can fail to recognize when followers
want a concrete plan and want to know that the details
are important to the leader. Knowing when to moderate
both assertiveness and emotional expressiveness helps
those with this leading style.

vw Systematic Style leaders can fail to recognize that a fol-
lower wants more brainstorming of possibilities and
greater enthusiasm about working together. Knowing
when to elevate both assertiveness and emotional
expressiveness benefits those with this leading style.

vr Considerate Style leaders can fail to recognize that a
follower wants more directness and more attention to
developing a plan to balance out the focus on empa-
thetic interactions. Knowing when to elevate an assertive
response and decrease emotional expressiveness ben-
efits those with this leading style.

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include:

vr Ask followers if more or less assertiveness would benefit
the working relationship with a question such as “Would
you like for me to be more direct?”

vr Ask followers if more or less emotional expressiveness
would benefit the working relationship with a question
such as “How can I be more supportive of your efforts?”

vr Monitor the time you spend “telling” versus “asking” in
an interaction. If you haven't heard from your followers
in the last 60 seconds, you're talking too much.

Chapter 4: Applying the Four Styles in Leading 3 5

= vr Evaluate the pace that you attend to and work through
© leading elements and processes

Of course the best leaders seek and respond to feedback
about what is working with the followers and what is neces-
sary to reach a goal. And sometimes the leader needs a coach
to clarify what aspects of the personality style need flexing.

36 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 5

Applying the Four Styles
in Teaming

In This Chapter
Discovering the key elements of teaming

Identifying the good and bad of the four personality styles in teaming

Flexing the four personality styles in teaming

= = BE NE NE NEE © 5 NEN SS EE BN BE NE I IE BE EE EE

Ts are made up of people working collectively to solve
problems, create new products, improve systems, and
reach goals that can’t be achieved by one or two people alone.
A team is more than a working discussion or problem-solving
group. Teams go through stages of development and require
the fulfillment of various roles and methods to produce synergy
and collaborative efforts. In all phases of teaming, interacting
with team members means that personality styles play a role

in how well the team really works together. Communicating,
problem-solving, planning, managing expertise, and addressing
conflict are a few of the processes of teams where the outcome
is dramatically affected by personality styles.

Because teaming situations often require working extended
periods of time with individuals across the organization,
differences in perspective, strategy, and “how to get things
done” are magnified by personality style differences. The
team member who walks into the meeting room and immedi-
ately puts an agenda on the wall is engaging differently from
the team member who walks in, talks with everyone, and gives
handshakes and back slaps while telling stories about last
weekend’s game. Without understanding differences, these
two could easily interfere with getting to the task at hand
and create unnecessary conflict. You should know your team

38 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

member style and understand the different styles you're likely
to work with. Knowing this information may enhance your
effectiveness on teams.

There are numerous team models and theories you can
research and read about. All these models, however, have
four basic elements that are present in team interactions and
processes:

vr Establishing a connection among team members so
everyone is clear as to why they're members of the team
or involved at a particular time in the process

vw Creating a common understanding of the goals, methods,
and plans for the team to do its work

vw Supporting each other in fulfilling the mutually agreed on
plan

vr Monitoring progress and re-evaluating future courses of
_ action

As you engage in each of these elements of teaming, the use
of your personality style reveals your team member style.
Importantly, learning to flex your personality style enhances
your team member effectiveness as you engage with team
members through each element of teaming. Your team behav-
ior combined with your personality style makes up your team
member style.

All team member styles can be equally effective but not
equally effective at all times. Team members need to flex their
style to work closely with others and to address the demands
of the team situation. You need to understand the benefits
and potential challenges of each style and consider how to
flex your style to work effectively with others.

The Good and Bad of the Four
Personality Styles as

a Team Member

Being a member of a team requires engaging with others to
find the best solutions to challenges brought to the team.

Chapter 5: Applying the Four Styles in Teaming 39

Your personality style greatly influences how you do this and
is represented in how you build trust, encourage actions, and
celebrate the results of team performance. In this section, you
see how the four styles can be useful in team situations, and
conversely, how they can create challenges.

Direct Style

The Direct Style works best when the team needs direction
and team members want someone to take charge. This style
says, “I know what needs to be done and here’s how we
should do it!”

A few benefits of this style as a team member include
vr Communicates assertively by asking difficult questions

and raising tough issues

vr Forward thinker and initiator of a course of action and
decision-making processes

vr Provides candid, decisive opinions on achieving a final
outcome

You may also notice a few trouble spots:
vr Appearing overly critical, which interferes with establish-
ing rapport and closes down group discussions

vr Seeming impatient and too open to taking risks, which
interferes with mutual planning and problem-solving

vr Displaying assertive behaviors, which leaves some of the
other team members feeling unsupported and discouraged

This style doesn’t work well when team members are cautious
and like to stick with established, safe processes.

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style works best when team members are open
to exploring new options and being spontaneous. This style
says, “I have some great ideas. What if we . . . or considered...
and maybe looked at . . ..”

450 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Take notice of these benefits:

vw Creatively provides the team with a fresh outlook

vw Brings high energy and fun to the team, motivating
others with their enthusiasm

vr Remains open to change and is quick to recognize and
©. praise others’ contributions

But take caution with the trouble areas:

vr Energy and enthusiasm may overwhelm others and cause
them to be seen as distracted and undisciplined

= WW The desire to generate new ideas and discuss options
can hold up decision-making and result in missed
deadlines

vr A high level of spontaneity makes it difficult to stick to an
© agenda

This style doesn’t work well when team members want an
organized, focused approach. Teams that need a planned
approach to understanding their issues or challenges won’t
work well with this style.

Systematic Style

This style works best when the team members want a detailed
plan that’s data-focused and pragmatic. Team members who
work best with this style want an objective, methodical team
member strategy. This style says, “With careful planning and
organization of priorities, we can meet our deadline and get
on to the next issue to solve.”

Those who favor this style provide the following benefits:

vr Thorough attention to process, which builds confidence
in the team plan

vr Focuses on facts, not feelings, which generates a clear
understanding of what needs to be done

vr Keeps the team focused on the priorities of the moment

Chapter 5: Applying the Four Styles in Teaming h 7

Potential trouble spots that may cause those with this style to
conflict with others:

1 A reluctance to try new approaches to problem-solving
or new tactics in implementing solutions

vr Taking too much time to work through each process, gen-
erating irritation and loss of focus by some team members

vw Failing to see the long-term big picture and being unable
to quickly flex strategy to meet changing demands

This style doesn’t work well when team members need a more
creative, less structured approach. Team members who are
looking for more mutual brainstorming and exploration of
ideas will find this style difficult in a teaming relationship.

Considerate Style

Those with the Considerate Style work best with team mem-
bers who want an empathetic, supportive, and encouraging
colleague. Team members who need a friendly relationship
will work well with this style. This style says, “I'm interested
in your perspective. What do you think?”

The benefits of the Considerate Style as a team member include
= Building a trusting, collaborative relationship with team
members

vw Listening actively and mediating conflict within the team

» Remaining flexible and being comfortable in taking on
less high-profile tasks

As with all styles, there is potential for trouble. Those with
the Considerate Style should beware of potential blockers to
their success:

=” This person becomes so focused on harmony that they can
appear passive or dependent to other team members.

Wr The desire to help others creates an imbalance within
team tasks and a feeling of being overwhelmed.

vw With building relationships being the key focus, impor-
tant tasks or details may be overlooked.

h2 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

This style doesn’t work well when team members want a more
decisive and independent approach. This style tends to take

a passive approach to challenges that won’t work for some
team members.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Teaming

To increase overall effectiveness, team members need to
learn to flex their style as the situation requires. For example,
the following elements of teaming may be more efficiently
achieved with different styles:

~~ Establishing a connection among team members so

everyone is clear as to why they're members of the team
7 or involved at a particular time in the process is natural
to the Considerate Team Member Style.

vr Creating a common understanding of the goals, methods,
and plans for the team to do its work comes naturally to
the Systematic Team Member Style.

=” Supporting each other in fulfilling the mutually agreed on
plan is easily energized by the Spirited Team Member
Style.

\ v“ Monitoring progress and re-evaluating future courses of
. action comes easily to the Direct Team Member Style.

Of course, an important determinant of the success of team-
ing processes is how well each style’s benefits are used by
the team and how well each team member flexes to work with
others who are different. If a Considerate Team Member Style
attempts to work with a Direct Team Member Style and nei-
ther knows how to flex, then the teaming efforts are likely to
be short lived.

Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the interaction
and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a response.
You need to determine how much assertiveness and emo-
tional expressiveness is required of you in an interaction.

Chapter 5: Applying the Four Styles in Teaming 43

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four team
member styles are as follows:

vr Direct Style Team Members can fail to recognize that a
team member's feelings have been hurt by a direct com-
ment or that other team members want to move at a dif-
ferent pace. Knowing when to increase some emotional
expressiveness and tone down assertiveness benefits
those with this Team Member Style.

vr Spirited Style Team Members can fail to recognize when
the team wants a concrete plan and wants to know that
the details are important to the team. Knowing when to
moderate both assertiveness (around ideas) and emotional
expressiveness helps those with this Team Member Style.

vr Systematic Style Team Members can fail to recognize
that a team member wants more brainstorming of pos-
sibilities and greater enthusiasm about the relationship.
Knowing when to elevate both assertiveness and emo-
tional expressiveness benefits those with this style.

vv“ Considerate Style Team Members can fail to recognize
that a team member wants more directness and more
attention to developing a plan to balance out the focus
on empathetic interactions. Knowing when to elevate an
assertive response and decrease emotional expressive-
ness benefits those with this Team Member Style.

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include

= ” Ask the team if more or less assertiveness would benefit
the interaction with questions such as “Would it be help-
ful if I outlined a plan?”

1” Ask the team if more or less emotional expressiveness
would benefit the interaction with questions such as “How
can we be supportive of each other in reaching this goal?”

1» Monitor the time you spend “telling” versus “asking” in
an interaction. Get some feedback from other team mem-
bers about the amount of time you spend speaking.

8 vr“ Evaluate the pace of moving through teaming elements
and processes by asking if the pace is working for others
and if new information can confirm the selected direction.

bl Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Of course, the best team members regularly seek and respond
to feedback about what is working in the team process. And
sometimes each team member needs a coach to clarify what
aspects of their personality style needs flexing.

Chapter 6

Applying the Four Styles
in Selling

In This Chapter

+ Looking at the fundamentals of selling

+ Understanding the benefits and trouble spots of the four personality
styles in selling

= Flexing personality style in selling

Sone a service or product, whether tangible, or intan-
gible, requires four key elements:

vr Introducing the product or service to the customer in a
way that builds credibility and trust

vw Identifying and explaining the pros of your item and
cons of other similar or parallel products or services to
elevate the customer’s interest

vr Responding to the expectations of the customer to foster
trust and connection

vw Closing the deal and fulfilling the order

The selling professional who does not understand how to
leverage personality style will have poor commissions. The
importance of personality style in selling is acute at two
levels: aligning of the styles of the seller and buyer and using
the right style in the right element of the selling process.

Matching styles between seller and buyer may mean a slight
shift in degrees of assertiveness or reaching out to make an
emotional connection. The best sales people know that you

h6 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

have to read the buyer’s style when approaching a product
or service deal and assume you will need to flex your style to
make the deal. But alignment is not enough. Each element of
the sales process requires a somewhat different approach,
often subtly shifting degrees of assertiveness and expressive-
ness. You'll succeed at both the alignment and approach if
you are clear about the characteristics of each styles and the
best use of each style as reviewed below.

As you engage in each of these elements of selling from prod-
uct interest to sales fulfillment, the use of your personality
style reveals your selling style. Importantly, learning to flex
your selling style enhances your selling effectiveness as you
engage with buyers through each element of selling. Your sell-
ing behavior and your personality style make up your selling
style.

All selling styles can be equally effective; although, selling
styles that don’t match the needs of the buyer can result in a
failed sell. You need to understand the benefits and potential
challenges each style tends to demonstrate.

The best sales professionals connect with the buyer in a style
that facilitates the sale.

Benefits and Challenges
of the Four Personality
Styles in Selling

Building a successful sales relationship can be challenging. The
buyer wants to trust the seller and believe that the seller is
looking out for everyone’s best interest in the relationship. The
comfort that a buyer has with a seller depends on both of their
personality styles. In this section, you discover how the four
personality styles benefit and challenge a sales relationship.

Direct Style

The Direct Style works best when buyers need direction and
decisiveness. A few benefits of this sales style include

Chapter 6: Applying the Four Styles in Selling h 7

= Being highly goal-oriented and not afraid to ask for the
business

vr Skilled at controlling sales conversations and staying
focused on the end result

vr Confidently outlining a plan of action for acquiring a
product or service

There are also the potential trouble spots to look out for:

vr Underestimating the value of developing relationships,
which interferes with establishing rapport and customer
interest

vr Seeming overly aggressive, which interferes with estab-
lishing credibility

vw Singularly focusing on the goal, which can leave the
buyer feeling pressured

This selling style doesn’t work well when buyers are looking
for a more personal, customer-oriented relationship. Buyers
who are looking for a nurturing relationship will find this style
difficult in a sales relationship.

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style works best when the buyer enjoys an
enthusiastic, high-energy approach. Some of the benefits of
this style include the following:

Wr Focusing on generating excitement about a product or
service

vw Creatively addressing customer questions and
observations

vr Developing a personal relationship and identifying extra
benefits for customers

You may also see the following trouble spots:

vr A high level of energy and enthusiasm, leading to exag-
gerated claims

vw The tendency to talk more than listen to the client’s needs

v» Failing to prepare well and missing important details

£8 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

This style doesn’t work well when buyers want an organized
approach. Buyers who need a planned approach to dealing
with their issues or challenges won’t work well with this style.

Systematic Style

This style works best when the buyer wants a detailed set

of criteria and a plan for making the purchase. Buyers who
work best with this style want an objective, methodical selling
strategy.

The Systematic Style lends itself to the following benefits:

vr Provides thorough attention to product or service
benefits

purchase

vr Sees rejection as an opportunity to refine the sales
. process

When the benefits of this style are taken to the extreme, the
following trouble spots may surface:

vr Reluctance to try new approaches or flex information to
the needs of the buyer

vr Too much time spent working through each part of the
process, leaving the customer feeling that the time to
complete the sale is longer than the product requires

vr Failing to see the long-term big picture such that the
buyer has doubts about the deal

This style doesn’t work well when buyers need an enthusias-
tic approach from the seller to build excitement. Buyers who
are looking for a more personal, less pragmatic approach may
find this style difficult in a sales relationship.

Considerate Style

The Considerate Style works best when buyers want an
empathetic, supportive, and encouraging interaction with the

Chapter 6: Applying the Four Styles in Selling h 9
seller. Buyers who need a friendly relationship work well with
this style.

The benefits of the Considerate Style in a sales relationship
include the following:

| kg Excelling at building long-term, repeat sales relationships

Listening attentively to the customer’s needs and provid-
ing support during all stages of the selling process

_ / Remaining patient with challenging customers

The following trouble spots may appear with the Considerate
Sales Style:

Becoming emotionally invested and taking rejection
personally

| vr Being overly focused on the relationship and less so on
closing the sale

vr Struggling when customers’ needs can’t be met

This style doesn’t work well when buyers want a more infor-
mative, product-focused approach. Buyers who are looking
for a “strictly business” approach may not work well with
this style.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Selling

To increase overall effectiveness, sellers need to learn to flex
their style as the situation requires. For example, the follow-

ing elements of selling may be more efficiently achieved with
different styles:

1” Establishing a relationship is easily achieved with the
Considerate Style.

vw Creating a common understanding of the benefits and
advantages of a product or services flows from the
Systematic Style.

50 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

vr Responding to the expectations of the customer and
building confidence in the product or service comes
naturally to the Spirited Style.

vw Closing the deal and working toward fulfillment of the
order is effectively managed with the Direct Style.

Of course, the most important determinant of the sales pro-
cess is the fit of seller style and seller knowledge with the
needs and style of the buyer. If a Considerate Style seller
attempts to work with a Direct Style buyer and neither knows
how to flex, then the selling experience is likely to be short
lived.

Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the interaction
and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a response.
You need to determine how much assertiveness and emo-
tional expressiveness is required of you in an interaction.

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four selling
styles are as follows:

= vw” Direct Style sellers can fail to recognize that a buyer was
offended by a direct comment or that a buyer wants to
move at a different pace. Knowing when to increase some
emotional expressiveness and tone down assertiveness
benefits those with this selling style.

vw Spirited Style sellers can fail to recognize when the
buyer wants a concrete plan and wants to know what the
details are related to the product or service. Knowing
when to moderate both assertiveness (around informa-
tion) and emotional expressiveness benefits those with
this selling style.

vr Systematic Style sellers can fail to recognize that a buyer
wants more brainstorming of possibilities and greater
enthusiasm about the product or service. Knowing when
to elevate both assertiveness and emotional expressive-
ness helps those with this selling style.

vr Considerate Style sellers can fail to recognize that a buyer
wants more directness and more attention to the explana-
tion of benefits and features as a balance to their focus
on warm and empathetic interactions. Knowing when to
elevate an assertive response and decrease emotional
expressiveness benefits those with this selling style.

Chapter 6: Applying the Four Styles in Selling 5 7

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include

vr Ask the buyer if more or less assertiveness would benefit
the interaction with a question such as “Would you like
for me to cover all the features of this product now?”

vr Ask the buyer if a more or a less personal approach
would benefit the interaction with a question such as
“How can I help you identify how this product meets
your needs?”

vr Monitor the time you spend “telling” versus “asking” in
an interaction. If you haven’t heard the customer’s voice
in the last 60 seconds, you're talking too much.

vr Evaluate the pace of moving through selling elements
and processes.

Of course the best sellers seek and respond to feedback about
what is working in the selling relationship. And sometimes the
seller needs a coach to clarify what aspects of the personality
style need flexing.

52 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 7

Applying the Four Styles
in Time Management

In This Chapter

% Checking out the elements of time management

% Knowing the benefits and weak spots of personality style in time
management

% Flexing the four personality styles in time management

| management isn’t just about how you accomplish
daily tasks or long-term projects, it’s also about the inter-
actions you have with others. Your day is filled, not only with
individual tasks but also with one-on-one and group inter-
actions. How you manage your time varies from person to
person, and these differences show up in everything you do.
To fully understand time style, it’s important to learn how it
drives behaviors and affects daily interactions and choices for
spending time on tasks.

Your level of assertiveness and expressiveness affects how
you manage time, resulting in your time management style.
More assertive people tend to channel their energy into
completing tasks quickly, while less assertive people prefer
a slower pace where all details are fully examined and every-
one’s needs are accounted for. Less expressive people prefer
less personal contact and more analysis time, while more
expressive people prefer spontaneity over planning.

All time management styles can be equally effective but not

in all situations. You may need to flex your style to complete
certain projects, juggle multiple tasks, or work with those who
have other time management styles. To do so efficiently, you

50 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

need to understand the benefits and potential challenges
of each style and consider how to flex your style in any
situation.

Benefits and Trouble Spots of
the Four Personality Styles
in Time Management

WING!
SS

Time is nonrenewable, so how you use it is important. Your
personality style can help you become efficient, but it can
also create barriers to your success. The four styles approach
the use of time differently. In this section, you find out how to
use the four personality styles to leverage your strengths and
minimize the behaviors that have the potential to cause you
problems.

Direct Style

The Direct Style works best when time is of the essence.
Those with this style show a singular drive toward a goal,
which moves tasks along quickly.

The benefits of the Direct Style in time management include
the following:

. vr Makes quick decisions

= Has immediate access to needed items

Along with the benefits of the Direct Style, there are also
potential trouble areas:

~~ Neglecting important details by focusing only on the
7 outcome

This style doesn’t work well when there are a lot of small
details to consider.

\NG/
oN

Chapter 7: Applying the Four Styles in Time Management 55

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style works best when there are multiple tasks to
be done and decisions to be made.

The benefits to time management highlighted by this style are:

ws Inspires and motivates others to move a project along

vr“ Enthusiastically starts new projects and handles multiple
projects with ease

Alongside the many benefits to time management for this
style, the potential trouble spots show up in the following
ways:

vr Becoming easily distracted

vw Letting spontaneous discussions eclipse the tasks at
hand

: v» Finding it difficult to complete tasks and organize their

workspace

The Spirited Style doesn’t work well with tight deadlines
because they have the potential to lose focus.

Systematic Style

People with the Systematic Style work best when a project
depends on careful planning and organization. The benefits
of the Systematic Style in time management are shown in the
following ways:

done right

vr Following procedure carefully

= V Being thorough and detail-oriented

Potential pitfalls to be aware of with the Systematic Style:

56 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

WNG/
S

=” Taking too long to make decisions

7 vr Missing signs of personal discomfort that could stall a

© project

This style doesn’t work well with tight deadlines as they can
get wrapped up in the small details and lose sight of the big
picture.

Considerate Style

The Considerate Style works best when decisions can be
based on others’ needs.

The benefits of the Considerate Style in time management
include

+” Not leaving enough time to complete work

vr Feeling uncomfortable with pushing through projects
without consensus

= vr Taking on too much and feeling overwhelmed

This style doesn’t work well when moving forward on a task
may offend or upset others.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Time Management

To increase your overall effectiveness, figure out a way to
flex your style as the situation and task require. For example,
the following elements of time management may be more effi-
ciently achieved with different styles:

Chapter 7: Applying the Four Styles in Time Management 5 7

= Establishing consensus in group tasks is effectively
achieved by the Considerate Style.

vr Getting the task done correctly the first time is effectively
achieved by the Systematic Style.

vs Finding new and innovative ways to complete tasks is
effectively achieved by the Spirited Style.

vr“ Keeping an eye on the goal and staying focused is effec-
tively achieved with the Direct Style.

An important determinant of the success of time manage-
ment is whether tasks are completed correctly and in a timely
manner. When so many demands are placed on your time, the
sequencing of tasks also becomes essential to effective time
management.

Because there are so many important aspects to time manage-
ment, learning to flex your style is essential. The Systematic
style may be great for getting it done right but may take an
extra month to get done, while the Direct Style may meet the
deadline but gloss over some of the details that they feel are
unimportant. Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the
situation and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a
response.

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four time man-
agement styles are as follows:

=” Direct Time Management Style can result in a failure to
recognize the value of others’ viewpoints. Taking the
time to get feedback from others or holding a focus
group can result in a better outcome for those with this
style.

vw Spirited Time Management Style can cause you to get
carried away with finding creative alternative processes
and lose sight of the finish line. Setting firm deadlines
and sticking to them benefits those with this style.

vr Systematic Time Management Style can cause you to get
so wrapped up in the details and process that you miss
deadlines. Keeping the big picture in mind benefits those
with this style.

58 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

vr Considerate Time Management Style can result in so
much time being spent helping others that you take on
too much and don’t complete your own tasks. Keeping
your own needs in the forefront benefits those with this
style.

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include:

= v Evaluate how much time you have to complete a task or
project. Are deadlines flexible? Are others waiting for
you?

vr Evaluate tasks. Is the big picture enough or do I need to
really focus on the small details?

vr Consider whether engaging others to explore alternative
processes may enhance the outcome.

w Prioritize current tasks. Is this urgent? Are others
depending on me to finish this now?

Of course the most effective time management results from
doing things correctly and meeting deadlines; however, it isn’t
always easy. Each task has different priorities, deadlines, and
associated skills. In some instances the deadline must be met
at all costs. In other instances the smallest details are vital

to success. Interpreting each situation and being able to flex
one’s style is essential.

Chapter 8

Applying the Four Styles
in Coaching

% Looking at the benefits and challenges of personality style in
coaching

» Flexing the four personality styles in coaching

magine one of the following situations:

vr You're helping a highly motivated employee deal with
a peer relationship issue.

vr You're coaching a peer about giving a presentation.

vw You're working with a volunteer group in need of your
expertise.

These situations are excellent for using your coaching skills
where you need to establish a trusting relationship with indi-
viduals. With a relationship of trust established, you use your
style to facilitate an understanding of what the individual
needs to do to improve performance. Coaches use their
experience, expertise, and insights to help others achieve
specific goals.

Effective coaches establish trust and rapport with their
coachees to create a collaborative process. Through mutual
understanding that leverages the knowledge of the coach and

60 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

needs of the coachee, coaching interactions motivate individ-
uals to change. Through listening, planning, goal setting, and a
variety of change techniques, coaches help coachees achieve
new levels of performance.

The basic elements of coaching include the following:

= Vf Establishing a relationship

vr Creating a common understanding of the issue and the
strategy for addressing the desired goals

vr Supporting the mutually agreed plan

vr Monitoring progress and re-evaluating future courses
of action

As you engage in each of these elements of coaching, the
use of your personality style reveals your coaching style.
Importantly, learning to flex your personality style enhances
your coaching effectiveness as you engage with coachees
through each element of coaching. Your coaching behavior
and your personality style make up your coaching style.

All four personality styles can be equally effective in coaching.
However, styles that don’t match the needs of the coachee
can result in a failed coaching relationship. You need to
understand the benefits and potential challenges each style
Er tends to demonstrate.
&

Anyone can be a coach regardless of position or role.

Looking at the Benefits and
Trouble Spots in Coaching

Your coaching style has the potential to work really well
with some coachees and not at all with others. The first step
in becoming a successful coach is understanding your style
and how it can be most effective in coaching situations. This
section helps you understand your own coaching behavioral
strengths and potential trouble spots and why your coaching
methods only work some of the time.

Chapter 8: Applying the Four Styles in Coaching 6 7

Direct Style

The Direct Style works best when coachees need to focus on
the end result and when they respond well to direct verbal
communication.

The benefits of the Direct Style in coaching include the
following:

1” Gets results

vw Assertively outlines a plan of action

wr Quickly corrects mistakes by providing solutions

In coaching, those with the Direct Style should watch out for
the following behaviors, which have the potential to turn into
trouble spots:

with establishing rapport
vr Jumping in too quickly to correct behaviors

vw Displaying highly competitive behaviors which interfere
with the coachee feeling supported

The Direct Style doesn’t work well when coachees are more
comfortable with a slower pace and a gentle touch.

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style works best when coachees enjoy a fun,
lively, less structured approach.

The benefits of the Spirited Style in coaching include

Wr Creative, spontaneous thinking

WW Creating an expressive, warm, and supportive environment

vr Generating motivation and excitement in others

Too much of a good thing can lead to the following trouble
spots for Spirited Coaches:

62 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

WING!

S

= Their energy and enthusiasm may overwhelm others,
preventing them from sharing their perspectives

vw They focus only on the big picture, which can lead to
overlooking the details and making generalizations

ww They get caught up in the excitement of new ideas, caus-
ing the coach to appear as impulsive and disorganized,
with poor time management skills

This style doesn’t work well when coachees want an organized,
detail-oriented approach. Coachees who need a planned
approach to understanding their issues or challenges don’t
work well with this style.

Systematic Style

The Systematic Style works best when the coachee wants
a detailed plan, with an attention to data and research.
Coachees who work best with this style want an objective,
methodical coaching strategy.

The benefits of the Systematic Style Coach are

vr Pays extreme attention to planning, process, and detail
vr Analytical and logical thinking
vr Presents a patient, reserved demeanor

The Systematic Style doesn’t work well when the following
behaviors surface:

= » Reluctance to try new approaches, which can block the
coachees’ creativity

vr Tendency to over-think processes, causing a slowdown
in forward movement

vw Failure to see the long-term big picture may present
~ roadblocks to success

This style doesn’t work well when coachees need a warmer,
less analytical coach. Coachees who are looking for creativity
and expressiveness find this style difficult in a coaching
relationship.

Chapter 8: Applying the Four Styles in Coaching 63

Considerate Style

The Considerate Style works best when coachees want an
empathetic, supportive, and encouraging coach. Coachees
who need a friendly relationship work well with this style.

The Benefits of the Considerate Style in coaching include

vr Encourages self-learning and personal insight

Vv” Listens actively and provides support during all stages of
the coaching process

vw Creates a comfortable, encouraging environment

The potential trouble behaviors to look out for with the
Considerate Style are

vr Overly focusing on rapport, which can lead them to
expect less from the coachee

vr Lacking directness, which may lead to a lack of clarity
about key issues or challenges

vr Rather than approaching some issues directly and with
initiative, spending too much time trying to facilitate per-
sonal insight

This style doesn’t work well when coachees want a more facil-
itative, results-oriented approach. This empathic style may
feel invasive to some coachees.

Coaching has become a billion dollar service industry and a
major training initiative for managers inside organizations.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Coaching

To increase overall effectiveness, coaches need to learn to
flex their style as the situation requires. For example, the fol-
lowing elements of coaching may be more efficiently achieved
with different styles:

Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

vr Establishing a relationship is efficiently achieved with the
Considerate Style.

vw Creating a common understanding of the issue and the
strategy for addressing the desired goals easily flows
from the Systematic Style.

vr Supporting the mutually agreed on plan comes naturally
to the Spirited Style.

vr Monitoring progress and re-evaluating future courses of
action is effectively managed with the Direct Style.

Of course, the most important determinant of the coach-

ing process is the fit of coaching style and knowledge of the
needs of the coachee. If a Considerate Style coach attempts
to work with a Direct Style coachee and neither knows how to
flex, then the coaching experience is likely to be short lived.

Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the interaction
and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a response.
You need to determine how much assertiveness and emo-
tional expressiveness is required of you in an interaction.

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four coaching
styles are related to shifting degrees of assertiveness and
expressiveness as follows:

=” Direct Style coaches can fail to recognize when a
coachee’s feelings have been hurt by a direct comment
or that a coachee wants to move at a different pace.
Knowing when to increase some emotional expressive-
ness and tone down assertiveness benefits those with
this coaching style.

w Spirited Style coaches can fail to recognize when the
coachee wants a concrete plan and needs to know that
the details are important to the coach. Knowing when
to moderate both assertiveness (around ideas) and
emotional expressiveness benefits those with this
coaching style.

vr Systematic Style coaches can fail to recognize that a
coachee wants more brainstorming of possibilities and
greater enthusiasm about the relationship. Knowing when
to elevate both assertiveness and emotional expressive-
ness can benefit those with this coaching style.

Chapter 8: Applying the Four Styles in Coaching 6 5

vr Considerate Style coaches can fail to recognize that a
. coachee wants more directness and more attention to
developing a plan to balance out the focus on empa-
thetic interactions. Knowing when to elevate an assertive
response and decrease emotional expressiveness may
benefit those with this coaching style.

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include the following:

~ Ask the coachee if more or less assertiveness would
benefit the interaction

) vr Ask the coachee if more or less emotional expressiveness
would benefit the interaction

=“ Monitor the time you spend “telling” versus “asking” in
an interaction

vw“ Evaluate the pace of moving through coaching elements
~ and processes

Of course the best coaches seek and respond to feedback
about what’s working in the coaching relationship. And some-
times the coach needs someone else to clarify what aspects of
the personality style need flexing.

66 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 9

Applying the Four Styles
in Learning

In This Chapter

+» Knowing the elements of learning

Grasping the benefits and challenges of the four styles in learning

» Flexing the four personality styles in learning

[ cone is the key to effectiveness in all aspects of life:
work, play, school, relationships, and any other endeavor
you can imagine. Learning has been studied from the neu-
rological to the behavioral level of human activity and a few
things are pretty conclusive:

= vr Learners use multiple styles more frequently and with
more ease than nonlearners.

vr Learners extract “lessons” from experience so that they
know what to do or avoid the next time they're in a simi-
lar situation.

vr Learners leverage their benefits and actively work to fill
gaps in their knowledge, skill, or behavior.

vr Learners overcome barriers to learning, especially the
. resistances they develop to learning.

What kind of learner are you? Do you think of learning as
something you do when you need to do something new or in
a different way at work or at home? Do you see experience as
a laboratory from which you can learn? Everyone was born to
be a learner; however, some may make the conscious choice
not to be a learner.

68 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Learners have been broadly grouped according to tactics

they employ in taking in information and acting on it. These
tactics are

vr Learning with others, the need to exchange information
and ideas

vr Learning through independent strategies which rarely
involve others

vw Learning through trial and error, taking action to test out
= anidea

vr Learning by thinking things through, personal analysis,
and the critique of information and options

As you engage in each of these learning tactics, the use of
your personality style reveals your learning style. Importantly,
flexing your personality and learning style enhances your
learning effectiveness.

All learning styles can be equally effective but not equally
effective at all times. Some learning styles work best in certain
situations. Your task is to make sure that you're using the
learning style that works best with the demands of the situa-
tion you are facing. You need to understand the benefits and
potential challenges each style tends to demonstrate.
SUNBER
& Learning means a change has occurred in behavior or
perspective.

The Pros and Cons of the Four
Personality Styles in Learning

Learning is a personal matter. Unlike being on a team or trying
to communicate a message, when you're in a learning situa-
tion, you approach information in your own unique way.

This way is influenced by your personality style. In this
section, you see how your personality style affects your
learning behaviors and provides ways to tackle new learning
challenges.

Chapter 9: Applying the Four Styles in Learning 69

WING!

&

Direct Style

Someone with the Direct Style learns best when taking control
of her own learning and is often motivated to learn by compet-
ing against herself and others.

The benefits of the Direct Style learner include

= » Taking charge to figure out what needs to be learned and
how to use the information

vr Remaining action-oriented and motivated when learning
something new

v» Thriving in a competitive environment, they quickly
absorb information to keep their edge

Along with the benefits, certain potentials for trouble exist
and are displayed in the following ways:

= v» Appearing impatient with help from others and ignoring
their own feelings about what is happening during the
learning

vr Seeming overly competitive about applying new learning,
resulting in incomplete application or premature applica-
tion of information

| vw Acting too quickly and not providing adequate reflection
on the information

The Direct Style doesn’t work well when a deep understand-
ing is necessary to fully learn new information.

Spirited Style

The Spirited Style learns best when she’s energetically
engaged with others, enjoying spontaneous brainstorming,
and emotional linkages to the new learning.

The benefits of this style come out in the following ways:

=” Showing enthusiasm for learning, even seeking out learn-
ing opportunities

Thriving at hands on learning, especially in groups

vw” Learning best through experimentation

70 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

WING/
SS . . ; ;
s As with all of the styles, there is a potential for trouble with

the Spirited Style. Be on the lookout for the following:

vr Energy and enthusiasm dimming if the learning challenge
is lengthy and layered

vr A tendency to disengage if learning is independent or rig-
idly structured

vr Neglecting to reflect on learning as they are already seek-
ing the next experience

The Spirited learner doesn’t work well when the learning
requires him to stay focused on one task for a long time.

Systematic Style

The Systematic Style learner is the most successful when he
or she creates a detailed plan and pays attention to specific
data. They are most effective as a learner when using an
objective, methodical strategy.

The following benefits apply to the Systematic Style Learner:
vr Comprehensively capturing information and making logi-
cal connections for how to use it

vr Highly organized and logical in processing learning

vr Thinking-oriented, with strong reading and researching
skills

S
The potential trouble areas for this style include:

vw” Finding informal and hands-on learning challenging

vr“ Spending time on items of little importance because of
the tendency to overanalyze

A Placing accuracy and logic ahead of feelings and emo-
tions, which tends to detach the person from others

This style doesn’t work well when trial-and-error learning is
necessary.

Chapter 9: Applying the Four Styles in Learning 7 7

Considerate Style

People with the Considerate Style learn best when informally
engaged with others in supportive and encouraging discus-
sions. As active listeners who take time to reflect, those with
this style learn effectively in friendly contexts.

The benefits of the Considerate Style include the following:

v» Encouraging support within a learning group, which is
the preferred learning atmosphere

| | vr Listening actively and reflecting on how the learning
makes him feel, as well as the impact it has on others

1” Processing diverse learning points

Awareness of the drawbacks to this style helps the Considerate
learner flex her style when the following behaviors come up:

the learning

vr Relying so much on the input of others that she has dif-
ficulty learning independently

vr Showing resistance to learning that changes the current
environment

This learner doesn’t work well when solitary learning is
necessary.

Flexing the Four Personality
Styles in Learning

To increase overall effectiveness as a learner, you need to flex
your style as the learning situation requires. For example, the
following learning tactics are natural extensions of the four
learning styles:

tion and ideas, is a natural aspect of the Spirited Learning
Style. For example, the Spirited learner is skilled at get-
ting everyone in a group to learn a procedure that needs
to be executed by everyone at the same time.

72 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

WING!
&

vr Learning through independent strategies, which rarely
involve others, is a natural aspect of the Systematic
Learning Style. For example, the Systematic learner is
skilled at learning how to apply a statistical formula to a
set of data.

vr Learning through trial and error or taking action to test
out an idea is a natural expression of the Direct Learning
Style. For example, the Direct learner is adept at learning
a sports movement.

1” Learning by thinking things through — personal analysis
and linking of information and choices — is a natural
aspect of the Considerate Learning Style. For example, a
Considerate learner is good at learning through a conver-
sation with an expert on a topic.

One of the most important determinants of learning effec-
tiveness is the fit of learning style and with the tactic that is
needed for the learning situation. If a Considerate Learning
Style attempts to use a Direct Learning Style tactic and it
doesn’t work with that learning situation, then the learning
may be short circuited.

Flexing requires you to assess the needs of the interaction
and to shift (even momentarily) in your choice of a response.
You need to determine how much control and direction
(assertiveness) and how much emotional connection (expres-
siveness) is required of you in a learning situation.

Some of the common flexing challenges for the four learning
styles are as follows:

© Rg Direct Learning Style individuals can fail to recognize the
role that personal, emotional reactions have in anchoring
information for later recall and fail to realize that learn-
ing different kinds of information may require a different
pace. Knowing when to increase some emotional aware-
ness and tone down a fast-paced, make-it-happen-now
approach benefits those with this style.

vw Spirited Learning Style individuals can fail to recognize

when learning requires a concrete, methodical plan and
when the details are important. Knowing when to mod-

erate both taking control (around ideas) and emotional
expressiveness benefits those with this style.

Chapter 9: Applying the Four Styles in Learning 73

vr Systematic Learning Style individuals can fail to recog-
nize the benefits of brainstorming and engaging others
in discussion about ideas. Knowing when to elevate
both assertiveness and emotional connections to engage
others benefits those with this style.

vr Considerate Learning Style individuals can fail to recog-
nize that more directness and less focus in their relation-
ship with others is necessary. Knowing when to elevate
and assert control over information and decrease emo-
tional connections and reactions related to information
benefits those with this style.

Tactics to use to enhance your awareness of when to flex
include

= Evaluate how much of the learning of a task or informa-
tion needs more independent and direct efforts

vr Think about how useful it would be to engage others in a
discussion about the information and to explore ideas to
enhance learning

vr Monitor the time you spend planning and outlining infor-
mation versus getting multiple perspectives and discuss-
ing key ideas and their application

vr Evaluate the pace of moving through information given
i its complexity, relevance, and clarity

Of course the best learners seek and respond to feedback
about what they learn and how they're learning it. The most
effective learners use all the tactics and styles frequently and
with deliberate effort to make sure they learn from all pos-
sible angles.

70 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 10

Top Behavioral Clues
to Identify Style

In This Chapter

+ Identifying someone’s style

= Dealing with situational style characteristics

HH a little trouble identifying someone’s style? This
chapter gives you questions that assist you in examin-

ing other people’s styles. Look at the situations in this chapter
and see which styles match up with those behaviors.

These everyday situations show just how easy it can be to
identify someone’s personality style. After you've identified
someone’s dominant style, think about the ways you can flex
your own style to maximize interactions with them.

Keep in mind that everyone is different, so people may not
show all of the characteristics of one style all of the time.
Someone with a dominant Direct personality style may also
have a fairly strong Spirited side.

MBER
SS
&

What Characteristics Do People
Display When Talking?

If you pay attention to others’ behaviors as you carry on a
conversation, you can pick up cues to their personality style.
Typical characteristics for each style include the following:

70 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

vw Direct: Gets to the point of a conversation quickly
vw Spirited: Tells good stories

vr Considerate: Doesn't offer opinions

vr Systematic: Precise in speech

What Kind of Listener Is He?

Defining what type of listener a person is can help lead you to
his personality style. Think about the following examples of
each style and see who comes to mind:

»” Direct: Can get impatient or distracted
| vw Spirited: Doesn’t hear details

| vr Considerate: Sympathetic listener

What Kind of Handshake
Does She Have?

A handshake can tell you a lot about a person, including clues
to her personality style. The list below shows typical charac-
teristics of each style:

vr Direct: Firm

vw Spirited: Enthusiastic

vr Considerate: Gentle

1” Systematic: Brief

How Does He Feel about
Personal Space?

Personal space can mean different things to different people.
Some people are very uncomfortable when others stand too

Chapter 10: Top Behavioral Clues to Identify Style 77

close, while others hug you every time they see you. To help
you identify each style, check out these characteristics:

= vr Direct: Maintains distance

vw Spirited: Likes to be close

=” Considerate: Comfortable giving and receiving a pat on
the back or a hug

~~ Systematic: Avoids touching

How Would Vou Describe
Her Movements?

You may not be aware of it, but your personality style can be
seen in the way you move. Are you a ball of energy jumping
from one thing to the next, or do you move at a more leisurely
pace? These behavioral characteristics relate back to your
style. The following descriptions help you identify each style
through a person’s movements:

vr Direct: Bold
vw Spirited: Quick

vr Considerate: Slow

+” Systematic: Controlled

How Would Vou Describe
His Workspace?

Are his walls covered with pictures of him and his friends to
remind him of fun times, or is his desk so organized that he
would notice if someone moved his stapler an inch to the left?
That’s his style’s influence. Below you find descriptions of
typical characteristics of each style in workspace organization:

78 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

vw Direct: Displays achievements, such as diplomas and
trophies

vw Spirited: Cluttered
vr Considerate: Displays photos

vr Systematic: Organized

Chapter 11

Top Rules for Interacting
Wıth Each Style

In This Chapter

t takes some willingness and effort to expand beyond your

own style to interact with others. The consideration of
others is generally appreciated, however, and may make the
difference between success and failure in an interaction.

In this chapter, you get the top five rules for interacting with
each personality style.

Taking on the Direct Style

Feeling intimidated by the strong, forceful Direct Style person-
ality? They aren’t as tough as they seem — just very focused.

To help your interactions go smoothly, keep in mind these
tips when dealing with the Direct Style:

1. Focus on the person’s goals and objectives.
2. Keep your relationship businesslike.

3. Be well organized.

4. Speak at a fast pace.

5. Ask direct questions.

80 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Keeping Up with the

Spirited Style
Have a co-worker who's full of energy and great ideas but
hard to work with because, well, she’s full of energy and great

ideas?

Try some of the following tips:

1. Be entertaining.

2. Engage in brainstorming.

3. Allow her to share her ideas freely.
4. Keep things moving.

5. Focus on inspiring ideas.

Cooperating with the
Considerate Style

No one can be that nice — he must have ulterior motives,
right? Nope, that’s just his Considerate Personality Style
coming through. He really does want to help and support you,
even at the expense of his own work. Go with it, but remem-
ber to return the favor.

To help you get the most out of your interactions, here are
some tips:

1. Focus on your relationship.

2. Be supportive of his feelings.

3. Make sure you understand his needs.
4. Maintain a relaxed pace.

5. Give him time to build trust in you.

Chapter 11: Top Rules for Interacting With Each Style $&7

Engaging with a Systematic
Style Person

When we say “just the facts, please,” we mean “just the facts,
please.” A Systematic Style person doesn’t have time for idle
chitchat or speculation; however, these detail-oriented people
are an asset to any project or team.

To make the most of your interactions with the Systematic
Style person, try the following tips:

1. Focus on facts, not opinions.
2. Be thorough and organized.
3. Avoid gimmicks.

4. Allow time for analysis.

5. Provide written evidence when possible.

8 2 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 12

Top Ten Personalıty
Style Tips

In This Chapter

» Paying attention to body language cues

+ Interpreting others’ actions

+ Appreciating the differences in people

+ Putting together a great team

P ersonality style is defined as the way people act when
they're able to do things their own way. This doesn’t

mean that people act the same way all the time, but behavior
is consistent to the point that it’s predictable. This chapter
contains the top ten Personality Style tips that help you make
the most out of your style and interactions with others.

No One Personality Style
Is Better Than Another

Which personality style is best? That question may be one of
the most frequently asked ones. The answer? In short, they all
are. Each style has its own unique characteristics that in the
right circumstance and at the right time come to the forefront.
Check out these instances:

= 1 In a situation where immediate, decisive action is
required, you'll appreciate the action-oriented Direct
Style.

8 h Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

= vr When a spreadsheet needs checking for accuracy, you'd
be wise to give this task to a person with the Systematic
Style.

vr Need to rally the team around a new initiative? Well,
that’s what people with the Spirited Style live for.

vr And if you have a problem and need to talk to someone
who'll be patient and listen, you could do worse than
X seek out someone with a Considerate Style.

Style Is Seen in Words, Tone of
Voice, and Nonverbal Actions

It’s not just the words you use. People read into the sounds
you make, whether harsh, pleasant, rapid, sarcastic, or what-
ever. People read into your nonverbal actions — whether
they're attentive, bored, or angry. Your expression and stance
may show how you truly feel. The way you stand, shake
hands, make eye contact, or not, all say just as much as the
words you choose.

Make your words, tone of voice, and actions consistent in
order to not confuse your message.

Knowing Your Style Helps Vou
See How Others See Vou

SOMBER Understanding your style and how you come across to others
& is an important step in developing stronger, more productive
relationships. In fact, understanding how others see you, and
learning to adapt according to their style, is one of the most
proven ways to increase your influence and personal success
in the workplace.

Why? Well, look at the core characteristics of your style (visit
Chapters 1 and 2 for more info). Now put yourself in the shoes
of a person with a different style. If you're a Systematic Style,
you may prefer to review the pertinent information before
making a decision. To someone with the Direct Style, who is

Chapter 12: Top Ten Personality Style Tips 8 5

oriented to take quick action, it may feel like you’re indecisive
and hesitant — not the basis for a great working relationship!

Knowing this information, you could choose, say, to offer
some preliminary thoughts on where you stand rather than
waiting to pore over every last detail before making your deci-
sion. By flexing your style, you meet the Direct Style’s prefer-
ence for speed. Win-win!

Flexing Vour Style Takes
Effort and Practice

In flexing your style, you need to adjust your behavior to
achieve a desired result. If you don’t flex, you're likely to expe-
rience frustration and disappointment in many situations. The
folks around you may feel the same way as you.

While all four styles are unique, there are compatibilities
between pairs of styles. Direct and Spirited people share the
same preference for assertive behaviors, and Spirited and
Considerate people share the same preference for expressive
behaviors. So there’s a good foundation to work on because
you only need to flex your expressive or assertive behaviors,
but not both.

You need to work a bit harder to build a better connection
with someone if you both share the style pairings of Direct/
Considerate or Spirited/Systematic because you both need to
flex your expressive and assertive behaviors, and this action
requires more effort. It may be uncomfortable at first, kind of
like writing with your opposite hand, but it gets easier with
practice.

The Strengths of Each Style
Can Be Carried to Extremes

Each personality style needs to learn how to limit the strengths
of her style in order to make the style not become abusive.
Extremes can be trouble spots and can become a problem.

8 6 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Some of the major factors in taking your style behaviors to
extremes include the following:

~V~ Stress

vr Being so extremely assertive (or not assertive) that you
lack balance in influencing others

vr Being so expressive (or not expressive) that you lack
balance in controlling your emotions

A strong emphasis on one style can mean a weakness in
another. For example, a highly objective person may find
himself neglecting people’s feelings.

Conflict Can Be Traced to
Differences in Personality
Styles

People get along with some folks more easily than they do
with others. While there can be a variety of reasons in play,
differences in personality style can often be at the root of the
problem.

Take a quick personality style audit of people with whom you
haven't established a strong connection but want to. Look for
any obvious differences in style, and then learn how to flex
your style to adjust your approach. Chapter 2 talks about flex-
ing specifically.

Recognizing Styles Helps Vou
Interpret Others’ Actions

Understanding the concepts of personal style and being able
to identify others’ styles helps you to interpret their actions.
For example, if Joe is generally friendly and outgoing, the fact
that he gives you an enthusiastic hello shouldn’t be inter-
preted as a sign of deep friendship. Joe probably gives an
enthusiastic hello to most co-workers. If, on the other hand,

Chapter 12: Top Ten Personality Style Tips 8 7

MBER
N
&

Joe is a private person and gives you an enthusiastic hello,
that signal may be taken correctly as a sign of friendship.

Knowledge of style sets up expectations of certain behaviors.
When the unexpected occurs, you can more accurately attach
meaning to it.

Differences of Style Should
Be Appreciated

Sometimes you may forget to thank the Direct person for
taking charge and initiating change or the Considerate person
for having a calm demeanor when the argument seemed to be
getting tense.

Take time to notice the differences you see in others, thank
people for what they’ve said or done, and especially thank
folks when what they have done is something that doesn’t
come naturally for you or them.

Mixing Styles Can Compensate
for Blind Spots on a Team

Competitive sports teams often comprise a high number of
Direct personality styles, which makes sense when you think
of the core characteristics of the style (for more on the Direct
Style, see Chapters 1 and 2).

Work teams, though, benefit from having a greater range of
styles. Diverse styles help the team compensate for possible
blind spots. The careful Considerate serves as a buffer to the
impatient Direct; Directs help push things through when the
Systematic prefers one more look at things. Each style helps
balance out the other.

When expanding or replacing a member of your team, it’s
worth taking into account the spread of styles, and, if it makes
sense to do so, consider people with styles that complement
what you already have.

88 Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Choose Work That Suits Vour
Personality Style

WNG/

If you find yourself having to flex your personality style too
much or too often, you may be doing the “wrong” kind of work
or be in a culture or environment that doesn’t suit you.

Look to your personality style for guidance as to the kind of
work or environments in which you're likely to thrive. If you
have a Systematic style and you prefer logical, straightfor-
ward assignments where you can work alone, a career that
offers this kind of work, such as Finance, would be a wise
choice. Considerate people are good listeners and value
personal relationships, and so they often choose careers in
counseling or the caring professions.

Personality
Style

FOR

HRDG SPECIAL EDITION

by Roger Pearman

WILEY
Wiley Publishing, Inc.

Personality Style For Dummies)? HRDQ Special Edition

Published by

Wiley Publishing, Inc.
111 River Street
Hoboken, NJ 07030-5774

www.wiley.com
Copyright © 2011 by Wiley Publishing, Inc., Indianapolis, Indiana
Published by Wiley Publishing, Inc., Indianapolis, Indiana

No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system or transmitted in any
form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, scanning or otherwise,
except as permitted under Sections 107 or 108 of the 1976 United States Copyright Act, without the
prior written permission of the Publisher. Requests to the Publisher for permission should be
addressed to the Permissions Department, John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 111 River Street, Hoboken, NJ
07030, (201) 748-6011, fax (201) 748-6008, or online at http: //www.wiley.com/go/permissions.

Trademarks: Wiley, the Wiley Publishing logo, For Dummies, the Dummies Man logo, A Reference
for the Rest of Us!, The Dummies Way, Dummies.com, Making Everything Easier, and related trade
dress are trademarks or registered trademarks of John Wiley & Sons, Inc. and/or its affiliates in the
United States and other countries, and may not be used without written permission. Myers-Briggs
Type Indicator is a trademark or registered trademark of the MBTI Trust, Inc., in the United States
and other countries. All other trademarks are the property of their respective owners. Wiley
Publishing, Inc., is not associated with any product or vendor mentioned in this book.

LIMIT OF LIABILITY/DISCLAIMER OF WARRANTY: THE PUBLISHER AND THE AUTHOR MAKE
NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES WITH RESPECT TO THE ACCURACY OR COMPLETE-
NESS OF THE CONTENTS OF THIS WORK AND SPECIFICALLY DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES,
INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION WARRANTIES OF FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
NO WARRANTY MAY BE CREATED OR EXTENDED BY SALES OR PROMOTIONAL MATERIALS.
THE ADVICE AND STRATEGIES CONTAINED HEREIN MAY NOT BE SUITABLE FOR EVERY SITU-
ATION. THIS WORK IS SOLD WITH THE UNDERSTANDING THAT THE PUBLISHER IS NOT
ENGAGED IN RENDERING LEGAL, ACCOUNTING, OR OTHER PROFESSIONAL SERVICES. IF PRO-
FESSIONAL ASSISTANCE IS REQUIRED, THE SERVICES OF A COMPETENT PROFESSIONAL
PERSON SHOULD BE SOUGHT. NEITHER THE PUBLISHER NOR THE AUTHOR SHALL BE LIABLE
FOR DAMAGES ARISING HEREFROM. THE FACT THAT AN ORGANIZATION OR WEBSITE IS
REFERRED TO IN THIS WORK AS A CITATION AND/OR A POTENTIAL SOURCE OF FURTHER
INFORMATION DOES NOT MEAN THAT THE AUTHOR OR THE PUBLISHER ENDORSES THE
INFORMATION THE ORGANIZATION OR WEBSITE MAY PROVIDE OR RECOMMENDATIONS IT
MAY MAKE. FURTHER, READERS SHOULD BE AWARE THAT INTERNET WEBSITES LISTED IN
THIS WORK MAY HAVE CHANGED OR DISAPPEARED BETWEEN WHEN THIS WORK WAS WRIT-
TEN AND WHEN IT IS READ.

For general information on our other products and services, please contact our Business
Development Department in the U.S. at 317-572-3205. For details on how to create a custom For
Dummies book for your business or organization, contact info@dummies.biz. For information
about licensing the For Dummies brand for products or services, contact
BrandedRights&Licenses@Wiley. com.

ISBN: 978-1-118-07696-5
Manufactured in the United States of America

1098765432

WILEY

Publisher’s Acknowledgments

We're proud of this book and of the people who worked on it. For details on how to
create a custom For Dummies book for your business or organization, contact info@
dummies. biz. For details on licensing the For Dummies brand for products or ser-
vices, contact BrandedRights&Licenses@Wiley. com.

Some of the people who helped bring this book to market include the following:

Acquisitions, Editorial, and Media Composition Services

Development Sr. Project Coordinator: Kristie Rees
Project Editor: Carrie A. Burchfield Layout and Graphics: Claudia Bell,
Editorial Manager: Rev Mengle Andrea Hornberger
Business Development Representative: Proofreader: Susan Moritz

Sue Blessing

Custom Publishing Project Specialist:
Michael Sullivan

Publishing and Editorial for Consumer Dummies
Diane Graves Steele, Vice President and Publisher, Consumer Dummies
Kristin Ferguson-Wagstaffe, Product Development Director, Consumer Dummies
Ensley Eikenburg, Associate Publisher, Travel
Kelly Regan, Editorial Director, Travel
Publishing and Editorial for Technology Dummies
Richard Swadley, Vice President and Executive Group Publisher
Andy Cummings, Vice President and Publisher
Composition Services
Debbie Stailey, Director of Composition Services
Business Development
Lisa Coleman, Director, New Market and Brand Development

Table of Contents

IntroducCHON ............,.....0000..5102200212 0000000 1
About This BOOK ee RR RER R RER E RR RER RR RE ER RERERREEEREEREGGG 1
About HRDQ esse rennt E REEL RE EEE EEERR RR REEEEEER RER REEEEERERREEEEEEG 1
How This Book Is Organized are ernennen nn EEE R ARE RKEEEKEEG 2
Icons Used in This BOOKaeeee ee rer rennen eG EEE EEE ERRREEEEGG 3
Where to Go from Here ass rent tE ER RER R RER E RR EEE E LEERE EEG 3

Chapter 1: Defining Personality Style ................ 5
Familiarizing Yourself with the Basics

of Personality Style ou... ern EEE EEE EEE RER E EEE EEE EEEEGG 5
Knowing What Makes Up a StYle....... een een 7
Checking Out the Four Personality Styles ass 9

Chapter 2: Deciphering Your Personality Style. ...... 13

Looking at the Elements of the Direct Style ......................... 13
Noticing the trouble spots of the Direct Style ........... 14
Making the Direct Style fleX........ ee 15

Understanding the Elements of the Spirited Style............... 15
Identifying the trouble SpOtS.......ee ee 16
Flexing the Spirited Style ee. 16

Sifting through the Systematic Style a... 17
Spotting the trouble areas..........cccccvveveeeecninniieenennnee, 17
Knowing how to flex the Systematic Style.................. 18

Comprehending the Considerate Style. au... 18
Uncovering the trouble spots

of the Considerate Style.........cccccvvvvvvvvvvvvvrrrnrrenrrnnneee, 19
Managing your StYle een EEE EEE 19
Chapter 3: Applying the Four Styles
in Communication.............................. 21
The Ins and Outs of the Four Personality Styles
in CommuniCation.........ccceeevviiiiieiiiieee cece, 22
Direct Style ......eeeeiieeeieeee eee, 23
Spirited Style ee... ee eee, 23
Systematic Style... eee, 24
Considerate Style... EEE EEE 25

Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Communication ...... 26

vi Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Chapter 4: Applying the Four Styles in Leading. ...... 29
Checking Out the Benefits and Trouble Spots
Of Each Style cocoon 30
Direct Style cocoon 30
Spirited Style a... 31
Systematic Style... eee 32
Considerate Style... EEE 32
Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Leading .................... 33
Chapter 5: Applying the Four Styles in Teaming ...... 37
The Good and Bad of the Four Personality Styles
as a Team MemMDeT are ee EEE EEE RER R EEE E EEE EEE E RE EEEG 38
Direct Style cc... 39
Spirited Style... 39
Systematic Style.......cccoovviiiiiiiiiiii een A RER R RER R EEE REEEEERGEG 40
Considerate StYleE.........e ernennen EEE EEE E EEE E EEE E ERREGT 41
Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Teaming................... 42
Chapter 6: Applying the Four Styles in Selling ....... 45
Benefits and Challenges of the Four Personality Styles
in Sellin essen EEE eee 46
Direct Style... 46
Spirited Style ee... E EEE R EEE E RER REERERERRERREREEEG 47
Systematic Style......cccccoeeiiiiiiiiii EEE EEE E RER R RE EEE EEEEEEG 48
Considerate Style... EE NEUEN 48
Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Selling...................... 49
Chapter 7: Applying the Four Styles
in Time Management........................... 53
Benefits and Trouble Spots of the Four Personality
Styles in Time Management essen 54
Direct Style cue 54
Spirited Style ee... EEE RER R RER R RER RR KK KR EEEEEEEG 55
Systematic Style... EEE EEE 55
Considerate Style... EEE EEE EEE E EEG 56
Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Time Management... 56
Chapter 8: Applying the Four Styles in Coaching ..... 59
Looking at the Benefits and Trouble Spots in Coaching..... 60
Direct Style ee... RER E EEE EEE eee 61

Spirited Style ee. R een 61

Systematic Style... ee R EEE ee 62
Considerate StYlE........ rer R RER R EEE E EEE E EEG 63
Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Coaching.................. 63
Chapter 9: Applying the Four Styles in Learning...... 67
The Pros and Cons of the Four Personality Styles
EEE 68
Direct Style... 69
Spirited Style... 69
Systematic Style.......oooooeiiiiiiiiiee, 70
Considerate Style..........cccooeeiiieeiiiieee eee, 71
Flexing the Four Personality Styles in Learning................... 71
Chapter 10: Top Behavioral Clues to Identify Style ...75
What Characteristics Do People Display When Talking?.... 75
What Kind of Listener Is He? een een, 76
What Kind of Handshake Does She Have? ........................... 76
How Does He Feel about Personal Space? ............................ 76
How Would You Describe Her Movements?......................... 77
How Would You Describe His Workspace? .......................... 77
Chapter 11: Top Rules for Interacting
With Each Style. 0.000000 79
Taking on the Direct StYle......ee ee EEE 79
Keeping Up with the Spirited StYle........ 80
Cooperating with the Considerate Style. a... 80
Engaging with a Systematic Style Person ............................ 81
Chapter 12: Top Ten Personality Style Tips .......... 83
No One Personality Style Is Better Than Another ............... 83
Style Is Seen in Words, Tone of Voice, and
Nonverbal Actions .........ccoooviiiiiiiiiiiiee cece, 84
Knowing Your Style Helps You See How Others See You......84
Flexing Your Style Takes Effort and Practice........................ 85
The Strengths of Each Style Can Be Carried to Extremes......85
Conflict Can Be Traced to Differences in Personality
STYLES... eee 86
Recognizing Styles Helps You Interpret Others’ Actions ......86
Differences of Style Should Be Appreciated......................... 87
Mixing Styles Can Compensate for Blind Spots
ON a T@AML.cccciiiiiiiiiieiiiiee eee eee eects cesarean 87

Table of Contents vii

Vill Personality Style For Dummies, HRDQ Special Edition

Personality style:
Why you act the way you do

If you find yourself wondering why your boss
never seems to hear what you're saying, or if you
struggle to find the best way to get your message
across to that key client, you need to understand
personality style. Knowing your personality style
provides useful insight into how you communicate,
lead others, work in teams, and a host of other
interactions. This book helps you discover your
own personality style and shows the effects —
positive and not-so-positive — your style can
have on others.

* Discover why you are who you are —
uncover the roots of personality style,
expressiveness, and assertiveness

* Master the HRDQ Style Model — learn a
simple but powerful way to understand
the characteristics, benefits, and potential
trouble spots associated with your style

° Flex for success — get tips and techniques
for increasing your influence and personal
effectiveness

Open the book and find:

* Practical ways to use
personality style in
everyday situations

* Ways to flex your style

* Tips for maximizing your

interactions with others
* How to spot others’ styles

* Ways to adapt your own
style to resonate with
others _

Making Everything Easier!™

Go to Dummies.come
for videos, step-by-step examples,
how-to articles, or to shop!

For Dummies®
A Branded Imprint of

WWILEY

ISBN: 978-1-118-07696-5

3|A1S AMIDUOSA3d

Sain 3

ueuwliead